Henry “Hank” Oyama Papers, 1945-2003(Bulk 1973-1980; 1991-2002)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Henry “Hank” Oyama Papers 1943-2003 bulk 1973-1980; 1991-2002
MS 448
Oyama, Henry
This collection contains the papers of Henry “Hank” Oyama that relates to his pioneering work in bilingual education in the Tucson area. Of particular interest are documents that discuss his work in bilingual education at Pima Community College. Included in the collection are newspaper clippings, correspondence, bilingual education research, and conference papers. There are also several publications related to Pima Community College and bilingual institutions in the greater Tucson area.
7.5 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None
Biographical Note
Henry “Hank” Oyama was born in 1926 and grew up in Mexico. He is of Japanese descent, and his first language is Spanish. His father died before he was born, and he was raised by his mother and maternal grandfather in Nogales. When his grandfather passed away, he and his mother moved to Tucson where they lived until the Japanese bombed Pearl Harbor in 1941. Oyama was fifteen years old at this time, and he and his mother were interned in concentration camps along with thousands of other Japanese and Japanese Americans. After the release of the internees, Oyama and his mother moved to Excelsior Springs, MO. Upon graduation from high school, he enlisted in the U.S. Army, and he was assigned to the Panama Canal Zone because his first language was Spanish.
In 1947, Oyama left the army and returned to civilian life where he earned a BA and MA in Education from the University of Arizona. Throughout college he worked for Tucson Newspapers, Inc. In 1952, he began his teaching career at Safford Junior High School in Tucson. Three years later, Oyama began his efforts in bilingual education when he was selected as a faculty member at the brand new Pueblo High School. At Pueblo, Oyama designed and executed a plan to teach both Spanish and English to native Spanish speakers. Through this program, he became involved with two U.S. senators who introduced national legislation to provide funding for bilingual education. At the age of 33, Oyama fell in love with Mary Ann Jordan. However, there was still a law in effect that banned marriage between Asians and Caucasians. After taking their battle to court, the two were married in 1959. Their first child died of leukemia, and they went on to adopt four children. They were married until Mary Ann’s death from heart failure in 1987 at the age of 55.
In 1970, he left Pueblo High School and began working for the Bilingual and International Studies at Pima Community College, becoming the dean of that program in 1978. He retired after 22 years at Pima Community College.
This collection is organized into 6 series.
Series I: Correspondence1945-2000s
Series II: Reports and Forms1960s-2001
Series III: Conferences, Meetings, and Events1966-2000
Series IV: Articles1967-2003
Series V: Newsletters1947, 1972-2000
Series VI: Publications1943, 1945, 1947, 1968-2003
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains correspondence; reports; files related to conferences and events; journal and newspaper articles; and publications. The time period represented in the collection is 1945-2003, but the bulk of the items are from 1973-1980 and 1991-2002. Most materials relate to Henry “Hank” Oyama’s involvement in the bilingual education movement in the Tucson area as well as his work for general Mexican-American rights. Reports and research for the reports make up the largest series in the collection. The reports are from all over the United States and relate to bilingual education and Hispanic issues. Of note in this series are Oyama’s handwritten notes referring to some of these reports. There is also a large amount of material dedicated to the English Only/English Plus More debates of the 1990s in Arizona.
Access Terms
Oyama, Henry,1926-
Education, Bilingual
Education, Bilingual – Arizona
Bilingualism
English-only movement
Mexican Americans – Arizona – Tucson; Education – Arizona – Tucson
- Series I: Correspondence, 1945-2000s
  This series is arranged alphabetically by subject and then chronologically by date. It contains letters to and from Henry Oyama during the war and throughout his career as an educator.
  - Confidential Info for Retirees (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Congreso, Jorge, Pepe, Alfredo (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Aug. 1945-Sept.1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Feb. 1979-June 1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, July 1992-Jan. 1999 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Jan. 1999-2000s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, File 7)
  - Folklorico Meeting/Funding Req., 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Garcia, George (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters of Acceptance B. B. Summer Institute "73 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters of Support for Bilingual Program, (1974) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - National Law Center for Inter-American Free Trade (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Need for Bilingual Secretaries (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Pima Community College Foundation, Hispanic Student Endowment Fund (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Sweetland, Monroe (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - A Tapestry of Tucson (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The White House, May 19, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Series II: Reports and Forms, 1960s-2001
  This series contains final reports, draft reports, and notes regarding research for reports on bilingual education and Hispanic issues. Some of the reports are written by Henry Oyama, but the majority is reports from various organizations involved in bilingual education and Mexican-American rights.
  - “1-C” Program (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on Diversity (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Agreement for Corrective Action (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Amphitheater Folklorico Board of Directors (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Application for Employment Institutional Support Personnel at PCC – Urquides, Maria L (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Arizona APS Economic Development Department (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Ariz. Association of Mexican Amer. Educators (AAMAE), 1972 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Ariz. Assoc. of Mexican Amer. Educators (AAMAE, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Bank of America Arizona 1994 Corporate Giving (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - The Biling and Int’l Prog. At PCC: A Successful Hybrid (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Biling. Courses (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Biling. Progs. and ESL (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Bilingual Training Program (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Bill to Amend Bilingual Education Act, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Diane V. Bissell/Raytheon; Sally Fernandez/Hughes (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Budget Draft (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - C. E. Rose, Robison/TUSD Biling. Educ (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Centro NAFIN para el Desarrollo de la Micro y Pequeña Empresa (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Coalition for Language Educ (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Combined Surveys, Conditions of Work for Quality Teaching, TEA (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Community as Resource for Minority Language Learning (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - CONALEP Automotive Prog (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - El Concilio para la Unidad Mexico Americana (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Congreso – General Info (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Dir., Biling. Educ. (Interview Questions) (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Educ. Center South – MDES (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Employee Evaluation – Oyama, Hank, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Eng. For the Children (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Eng. Plus More (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - English Plus More Mission Statement (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Fellowship Program (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Fimbres, Richard (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Fiscal Year 1971 EPDA Projects in support of bilingual education (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Folklorico Infantil (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Frederic Burk Foundation for Education at San Francisco State University (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Goals, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Goal Synthesis Process for Bilingual-Bicultural Education Using a Modified Delphi Technique, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Graduate and Undergraduate International Studies Program Development (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Grupo Folklorico de Pima College, performances, list of members (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Hernandez, Angel (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Higher Education Leadership Program (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Hispanic Businessmen PCC OBIS Biling. Admin. Prog (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Hispanic Professional Action Committee (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Hispanic Student Endowment Fund Select Committee (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Hispanic Studies (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Hispanic Studies Grades K-12 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - ICEED, New Summit Info, memo from Miguel to Carol (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Implementation of Prop 203 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Individual Member Form (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - The Initiative (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Instituto de Folklore Mexicano (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Interim Report (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Interim Report Revised Grant (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - International Center for Higher Education and Philanthropy (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - International Consortium for Educational and Economic Development, Annual Report of Activities of the Executive Directory, Jan. 23, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Introducing the Sunnyside Unified School District Foundation (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - The Invisible Minority (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Latino Adv. Comm. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Law and Poverty Class Project – Biling. Educ. In Tucson (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Lemos, Alfonso (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Lopez Plan (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - LULAC (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - LULAC (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - MACCA (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - MALDEF (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - MDES Decentralization Plan (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - MDES – Developmental Education (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Mickolajak, Gary (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Minera San Jorge S.A. de C.V. (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Misconceptions – Biling. Educ (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - ML, BB TC Institute Schedules, 1973 Biling. Inst. (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Molina, Marie Christina (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - MONTAL Educational Associates (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - National Ed. Task Force de la Raza (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - National Hispanic Scholarship Fund (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - National Law Center for Inter-American Free Trade (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - NEA – Tucson Survey on the Teaching of Spanish to the Spanish Speaking (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - New Mexico State University Program for the Department of Mexican-American Community College Admins. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - OBIS Survey, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - OME Ad Hoc Panel Reports (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Oyama, Henry’s Notes (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - PCC Biling. Educ. Development Prog., 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - PCC Danforth Proposal (including El Paso and Cochise proposals) (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - PCC EPDA (Part D) Proposals, Guadalajara Institutes Phases II, III, and IV (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - PCC Hispanic Enrollment (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - PCCF Planned Giving Committee Report, Dec.15, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Peralta, Mike (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - A Personal Position Paper on Leadership (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Las Posadas (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Position paper (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Prog. Eff. (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Program Proposal to Assist in the Development of Mexican-American College Administrators, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Program META (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Prop 227 The Initiative (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Proposal for Biling. Educ. Prog. at Pima College (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Proposal Outline for Biling. Educ. at Pima College (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Recommendations for Bilingual Program by Pauline Kelzer, Dec. 6, 1973 mtg. and other Info. (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Recommendations Regarding Biling. Courses at PCC, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - A Relook at Tucson ’66 and Beyond, Albuquerque, Nov.28-Dec. 1973 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Reports and Forms, Misc., 1963-Nov. 1998 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Reports and Forms, Misc. Nov. 1998-2000 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Report on Failure/Success Rates of Bilingual Students in Higher Education (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Revision: Bilingual Training and Curriculum Development (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Rosas, Gilbert A (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Rose Elem. Questionnaire (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - School Reports (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - John C. Scott/H.O.’s Bio, Ben Buehler Garcia fax #624-0955 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Self-Identity: Minority Affairs Subcommittee (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Southside Partnership Steering Committee (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Summary of Recommendations for Change in the Biling. Educ. Program Pima College (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - A Tapestry of Tucson (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Tapestry of Tucson African-American Contributions (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Thomas, Wayne P. and Virginia P. Collier, George Mason Univ. (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Title VI Int’l Proposal (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Tohono O’Odham Resolution Navajo Nation Proposed Resolution (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Training Program in Bilingual-Bicultural Education Final Report, June 30, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - TUSD (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - TUSD Biling. Ed. (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - TUSD Dropout Rates (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - TUSD Hispanic Studies. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - TUSD Parental Waivers Request, Effect of Prop 203 on Biling. Educ. and Teacher Training (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Tucson Convention Center Commission (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Tucson Metropolitan Chamber of Commerce (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Tucson Rotary Club (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - TRS Prog. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - TUSD Sch. Admin. Questionnaire (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - The University of Arizona Building the Future Class of 2007 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - University of California, Los Angeles: The Training of Mexican Americans for Leadership Roles in Community Colleges (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Useful Reports (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Viva Arizona (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Series III: Conferences, Meetings, and Events, 1966-2000
  This series includes minutes, programs, presentation notes, and invitations for various conferences, meetings, and events that Hank Oyama attended or participated in from the 1970s to the 2000s. Most events are related to his work in bilingual education, but a small number are of a personal nature.
  - 1C (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - 1st Nat’l Comm. and Jr. Col. Colloquium on Biling.-Bicultural Ed. (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - 3rd Anniversary Recognition Day Program for the Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. Student Center (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - 12th Annual Serra Scramble and Priest Appreciation Dinner (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - 15th Annual Bishop’s Scholarship Dinner, September 24, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - 25th Anniversary Dinner (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - AACHE (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - AACHE Celebration to Honor Eva Cota and Raquel Goldsmith (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - AACJC Convention Feb. 24-27, 1974, LTI Biling. Educators Wkshp. Feb. 28- Mar 1, 2, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - AACJC Convention 1976, Wash., D.C., Mar 15-21, 1976 and CONAC Reception (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Acción ‘80s (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - American Airlines Tickets (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Ariz. 1st Bilingual Institute (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Ariz. Association of Mexican American Educators (AAMAE) (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Arizona Education Association, Special Committee on Biling. Educ. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Arizona Language Education Council (ALEC) Presentation to HPAC, Wednesday July 5, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Ariz. Parents (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Arizona Parents’ Right to Sch. Choice vs. Arizona’s English Only Initiative (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Asian Community (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Asociacion de Charros de Tucson, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Bilingual Education 25 Year Anniversary Committee Meeting (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Biling. Educ. and School Choice Remarks by James Crawford (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Biling. Educ./Hispanic Studies and Second Language Acquisition Review Committee (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Bilingual/ESL Multi-Campus Meeting, Aug. 21, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Bilingual Pay Program (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - BOG CONALEP Presentation (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Business Administration Dinner, May 7, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - The Celebration of the Marriage of Elizabeth Murfee and Dino DeConcini, October 11, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - El Centro Cultural Annual Meeting, April 11, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Ciudad Obregon Visit (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - CONAC Curric Planning Conf. (Follow-up and Concluding Conf. of series of conferences that included Queretoro and El Paso conferences) (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - CONAC Meeting – Aug. 1974, Ajijic, Jalisco (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - CONALEP Trip to Mex. City, June 20-24, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - CONALEP Visit April 1992 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - CONALEP Visit to PCC (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Congreso Board Mtg. May 28, 1974 Goleta, California (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Congreso Mtg. – Seattle Apr. 12, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - El Congreso Nacional de Asuntos Colegiales: Parents – An Education Institute, Mar. 24-28, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Day of Dialog, SMCC (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - De Concini, Dennis meeting (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Desert Vista Campus, 2nd Bilingual Festival (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Educational Services Staff Meeting, Sept. 8, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - “English as a Second Language” Workshop (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Eng. Plus More Presentation (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - EPDA Institute, 1973-74 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Fiesta de la Placita (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - First Annual Ray Davies Luncheon, Educational Enrichment Foundation, October 20, 1999 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Golf for Education (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Guidelines for Local Conference Chair (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Handouts (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Hispanic Studies Symposium, May 11, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Hispanic Year 2000 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - ICEED/CONALEP (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - International Consortium for Educational and Economic Development (ICEED) Annual Meeting, January 21-23, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Israel 50th Anniversary (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - The Jefferson Awards, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Kiser, Jim Meeting (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Kolbe-HPAC Conference (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - KUAT Public Advisory Board Annual Meeting, May 19, 1999 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Latino Adv. Comm. (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Leadership Colloquium, January 11-14, 1981 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - LULAC Annual Awards Luncheon, October 29, 1999 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - LULAC Biling. Forum and Border Dispute (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - LULAC Council (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - LULAC Resolution and Fimbres/Oyama Presentation (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - LULAC State Meeting, April 5, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - LULAC State Meeting, January 30, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - LULAC Superintendents Recep. July 7th Inn Suites, Copper Room (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Luz Academy Spain Trip (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Los Mariachios de P.C.C. (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Meetings, Misc. (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Meeting with Carol Gorsuch 5-21-92 (Thursday) (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - National Secretaries Week Recognition Dinner, April 26, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - National Strategy Meeting on Defeating Arizona’s State Ballot Initiative Against Biling. Educ. (Box 9, Folder 31)
  - Una Noche Plateada (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - Opportunities for Improved International Understanding, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - Oyama, Henry: L.A. Symposium 5/24/77 (Box 9, Folder 34)
  - PCC Amigos de Pima Reunion Dinner 2003 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - PCC/CONALEP Dinner (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Peruvian Ministry of Education (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of Hank Oyama (photocopies) at events (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Pima Community College Fifth Annual Hispanic Celebration, May 15, 1999 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Pima Community College Foundation Fifteenth Annual Recognition Dinner, October 27, 1999 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Pima Community College’s 25th Anniversary (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Poesias, Cantos y Bailes del Pueblo (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Presentation Information (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Presentation on U.S.-Mexico Relations (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Prop 203/Biling. Educ. Issue (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Public Advisory Board Minutes, March 31, 1999 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Pueblo High School Class of 1962, 35th Year Reunion (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Refund – Aeromexico and America West (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Runnin’ at Midnite, December 4, 1999 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Self-Identity and the Use of “Minority” Terminology for the 21st Century (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - “Semana Cultural” (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Sister City Trip Oct. 22-26, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Sixth Annual Festival Folklorico de Ballet Folklorico San Juan, July 15-16, 1995 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Sponsors (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Staff Meetings (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Symposium of the Mexican-American Student, Apr. 1968 (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Symposium of the Spanish-Speaking Child in the Schools of the Southwest (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Symposium for Bilingual/Bicultural Manpower Development, Mar. 14-16, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - A Tapestry of Tucson Committee (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Tapestry of Tucson Committee Meeting, May 28, 1999 (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Tapestry Meeting, October 14, 1998 (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - Tickets Anniversary Dinner (Box 10, Folder 28)
  - Video Presentation (Box 10, Folder 29)
  - Vote No! 203 English Plus More (Box 10, Folder 30)
- Series IV: Articles, 1967-20003
  This series includes scholarly journal articles, newspaper clippings, and Internet articles related to bilingual education. There is a heavy emphasis on the English Only/English Plus More debate of the 1990s.
  - 25th Anniversary of Hank Oyama’s wedding (Box 10, Folder 31)
  - Ariz. Daily Star articles on biling. Educ.; English Only articles (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - Articles, Misc. 1967-2000 (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - Articles on Bilingual Education (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Asociación de Charros and Corazón de Oro (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Begaye, Kelsey A., Pres., Navajo Nation, Guest Editorial (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Biling. Educ. Articles (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Biling. Educ./H. Oyama (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Citizen Editorial June 9, 2000; Star Editorial April 24, 2000 and June 28, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Combs, Mary Carol – Official Eng. (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Current Biling. Articles (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Los Descendientes del Presidio de Tucson, January-June, 2003 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Drafts of Hughes Missile Systems Ad (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Eng. Only/Eng. Plus (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Eng. Plus (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - The Evolution of the Mariachi: A Brief Historical Sketch (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Hispanics Making a Difference (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Hispanophobia (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - IDRA (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Initiatives are too easy (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Krashen, S. (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Krashen, Stephen (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - A Language Deficit Theory for the 80s; CALP, BICS, and Semilingualism (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Latino Adv. Comm. (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - Mama’s Santos: An Arizona Life (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - MDES Decentralization Plan (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Meta (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - A Nation at Risk (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - National Law Center for Inter-American Free Trade (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Navajo Nation – Pres. Begaye (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper articles remembering WWII (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Noda, Dr. Phyliss (Radio Prog.) (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Not Child’s Play (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - The Odd Couple (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - The Pariah (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - PCC Biling. Educ. (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Post Election (Prop 203) Issues (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Read 1972, 1981, 1989-1992, 1996 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Relocation Camp Articles (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - The Rising Star, Winter 2002 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Rothstein, R. – Sink or Swim (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - A Systematic Approach to Total Quality Management (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - TUSD/Biling. Educ. Articles (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Vote No! 203 English Plus More (Box 12, Folder 19)